Hi there, today let's do some more work on not using boring words, not using the basic
ordinary English words for things and instead on developing your vocabulary further.
I did a podcast number 498 where I did the same exercise with words for good, so I gave
you a lot of different synonyms for good which will help your English language learning.
Hello, I'm Hillary and you're listening to Adapt English.
We will help you to speak English fluently or you have to do is listen, so start listening
now and find out how it works.
This podcast will help you sound more like a native English speaker and less like a beginner
at speaking English.
So let's develop your vocabulary, let's make it more vivid, not boring.
And today I'm going to do words for big or large.