Hi there, today let's do some more work on not using boring words, not using the basic
ordinary English words for things and instead on developing your vocabulary further.
I did a podcast number 498 where I did this same exercise with words for good, so I gave
you a lot of different synonyms for good which will help your English language learning.
Hello, I'm Hillary and you're listening to Adapt English.
We will help you to speak English fluently or you have to do is listen, so start listening
now and find out how it works.
This podcast will help you sound more like a native English speaker and less like a beginner
at speaking English.
So let's develop your vocabulary, let's make it more vivid, not boring.
And today I'm going to do words for big or large.
Useful in everyday conversation but also will elevate your level of English for any
IELTS or similar English language tests.
Adapt English provides a lot of free language learning services for people all across
the world.
And in particular our services are helpful to people in countries where they are prevented
by their government from buying English language learning courses.
So one of the ways in which you can support Adapt English and help us is simply by becoming
an Adapt English subscriber.
This helps us on platforms like YouTube and Spotify.
You know how this works.
The more subscribers we have, the higher up the rankings on YouTube and Spotify we go
and the more people who want to learn English get to find Adapt English.
We make sure our podcasts are good quality.
You can help us with our rankings by subscribing.
You can help us increase our number of listeners still further.
So don't forget, subscribe today on YouTube, on Spotify or wherever else you listen.
Thank you very much for doing that.
So today let's continue working on making your vocabulary vivid.
Let's continue helping you speak English in an interesting way.
It's one of the things that's really noticeable about beginners in a language.
You've got a restricted range of words and it's very noticeable on adjectives.
So words we use to describe nouns.
And given the podcast I gave you last week where I was talking about high frequency words,
there's nothing wrong with this.
But if you want to take your learning stage further and become an intermediate speaker of English
rather than the beginner, then knowing a greater variety of words, especially adjectives,
will be really helpful to you.
English always has a number of words for the same thing.
Synonyms if you like.
So today here goes for synonyms or words which mean the same.
Synonyms for big or large.
So big, BIG is a default word.
It's one you'll already know.
A mountain is big.
The NHS is big.
The landmass of Russia is big.
The other very normal default word for this is large LARGE.
Large and big are pretty much the same.
If anything large is a little more formal and big is a little more informal.
In a newspaper article I think the word LARGE would tend to be used, but you may also find
big.
So remember that word synonym, S-Y-N-O-N-Y-M.
And it means a different word but with the same meaning.
Here are some sentences for you which include some synonyms for large or big.
It's a giant tree.
They own several gigantic houses.
The mountain was huge.
There was a humongous gap between the platform and the train.
Her car is enormous and difficult to park.
The building was colossal.
It is with immense gratitude that I receive this donation.
That was a gargantuan meal that you cooked.
The auditorium was vast and silent.
So let's go through those adjectives.
That means you can replace one with another and there's not much difference in meaning.
They're not completely interchangeable though.
So the first sentence, it's a giant tree, T-R-E-E.
The word giant G-I-A-N-T.
It's a noun that's a word for a very, very large being.
You sort you meet in children's stories or perhaps in Tolkien, a magically large person,
like Gulliver from Gulliver's travels perhaps if you know that book.
So when we use giant as an adjective, we mean similarly large.
Something that's much bigger than you would expect.
Giant size, we get this on packaging.
It's a giant pack of whatever it is you're buying.
Similarly the word gigantic, G-I-G-A-N-T-I-C.
It's a related word and it comes from a similar word stem in Latin as giant.
If you suffer from the medical condition, giganticism, it means you're a giant.
You're abnormally big and large.
If there's a difference in use here, then possibly you're more likely to use giant
or gigantic about physical items rather than in an abstract way.
But that's not a firm rule.
Similarly the word gargantuan, G-I-R-G-A-N-T.
You-A-N.
Gargantuan is also related to giants.
Apparently it comes from a novel by the French writer Raba-Lay.
And one of his heroes is the giant gargantua.
Apparently this giant had an enormous throat to your throat down inside there.
What you used to swallow is, gargantua would eat people.
And this word may come from gargantua.
Don't know how to pronounce that, but that's a word in Spanish or Portuguese, meaning
throat.
So presumably gargantua had a big throat.
So that he could eat people.
Maybe that image will help you remember the word gargantuan.
Next ones, the mountain was huge.
There was a humongous gap between the train and the platform.
So these words are also related.
Huge is H-U-G-E.
That's much more common.
And probably pronunciation is the biggest challenge with that word, relating its spelling
with its pronunciation.
If you don't know the word huge, do have a look at how it's spelled H-U-G-E.
Huge and humongous, slightly less common.
So huge mongous, if anything, is probably slightly bigger than huge.
If something is humongous, it probably shocks and it stands you with its size.
Much the spelling on humongous as well.
H-U-M-O-N-G-O-U-S.
Humongous.
Next, enormous.
The n-O-R-M-O-U-S.
That is a good old-round word for very large.
And it's probably one of the more common ones.
Elephants are enormous.
It's slightly more usual as well to use enormous to describe abstract things, abstract words.
So words at an ideas level.
There's also a noun to go with enormous.
Inormity.
E-N-O-R-M-I-T-Y.
The enormity of the problem just became clear, for instance.
Colossal.
CO-L-O-S-S-A-L.
That's another one.
And the association of this word is fairly obvious.
If you think about buildings in ancient Rome, you'll think about the Colosseum, for instance.
The one that contained lions sometimes.
And Colossus, CO-L-O-S-S-U-S means an enormous statue in ancient Greece.
The Colossus of Rhodes is an example.
So Colossal is used to describe physical and abstract things that are very large.
You could talk about a Colossal task or a Colossal debt, even.
That's topical, isn't it?
The next one, immense.
This one, immense, is more often used of abstract nouns, perhaps, but it doesn't mean you
can't use it for physical things as well.
You might say it gave me immense pleasure to work with him, or he felt immense pride
in his work.
The last example I gave of words for very large, the auditorium was vast and silent.
That's a quote from Jim Morrison and the doors.
A good 1960's bound, if you know them.
vast, V-A-S-T, another adjective meaning very large, but vast is more often used of empty space.
A warehouse might be vast, or there are vast distances in outer space.
You might also hear vast used for quantity as well.
Vast songs of money is a phrase or vast amounts of rubbish.
So a quick rundown again of those words, different words for large or big synonyms, giant,
gigantic, gargantuan.
Huge, humongous, enormous, colossal, immense and vast.
Listen to this podcast a number of times until you are comfortable that you know all
of these words, so that you recognise them when you hear them, but perhaps also so that
you can use them when you speak.
That is enriching your vocabulary, making your vocabulary more vivid in English.
Have fun with it, surprise people with these words that you've learned.
Enough for now, have a lovely day, speak to you again soon.
Goodbye.
Thank you so much for listening.
Please help me tell others about this podcast by reviewing or rating it.
And please share it on social media.
You can find more listening lessons and a free English course at adapting.com.
Thank you.